Lukas Brunner

curriculum vitae





Research

I am passionate about understanding changes in global and regional climate as well as their drivers. My research includes work on the evolution of atmospheric blocking and its impacts, on the analysis of multi-model ensemble projections, and on aspects of model heritage and inter-dependence. I have published several Python packages and I am enthusiastic about all aspects of open science. My work also includes teaching, supervision, project coordination, and public outreach.

Professional Experience

2022 - present	Senior Scientist, Dep. of Meteorology and Geophysics, University of Vienna
2018 - 2021	Senior scientist, Institute for Atmospheric and Climate Science, ETH Zurich

2014 - 2018 Predoctoral scientist, Wegener Center, University of Graz, Austria

2017 Visiting scientist, Center for International Climate Research, Norway

2015 - 2016 Visiting scientist, School of Geosciences, University of Edinburgh, UK

Education

03/2018 Dr. rer. nat. in Climate physics, University of Graz, Austria

07/2014 MSc. in Geophysics, University of Graz, Austria

10/2012 **BSc. in Physics**, University of Graz, Austria

Selected publications

09/2019 L. Brunner, A. G. Pendergrass, F. Lehner, A. L. Merrifield, R. Lorenz, and R. Knutti: Reduced global warming from CMIP6 projections when weighting models by performance and independence. *Earth Syst. Dynam.*, https://doi.org/10.5194/esd-11-995-2020

11/2016 **L. Brunner**, G. C. Hegerl, and A. K. Steiner: Connecting atmospheric blocking to European temperature extremes in spring, *J. Climate*, https://doi.org/10.1175/JCLI-D-16-0518.1

Code

Detect blocking https://github.com/lukasbrunner/blocking

Model weighting https://docs.esmvaltool.org/en/latest/recipes/recipe climwip.html

Other

2019 - 2021 Board member (president in 2021), Club Alpbach Vorarlberg, Austria

2016 Marietta Blau Scholarship, Austrian Exchange Service